 Review of SDG implementation and interrelations among goals
Discussion on SDG 8 – Decent work and economic growth
Wednesday, 10 July 2019, 3:00 PM–6:00 PM, Conference Room 4
Background Note
Executive summary
SDG 8 promotes “sustained, inclusive and sustainable economic growth, full and productive employment and decent work for all”. It reaffirms the mutually supportive relationship between economic, social and environmental policies, full employment and decent work. Progress has generally been slow on the twelve interconnected SDG8 targets. Major gaps remain and progress has been uneven across regions. Some major emerging economies have enjoyed relatively strong economic growth and diversification, while others have fallen further behind. Many regions underperform on measures of inclusive and sustainable economic growth. Despite many progresses, not all the workforce is enjoying decent work.
Globally, labour productivity has increased and unemployment is back to pre-financial crisis levels. However, the global economy is growing at a slower rate and a worrying productivity gap is opening up between low income countries and middle income countries. More progress is needed to create decent work for all, including through increasing employment opportunities, particularly for young people, reducing informal employment and labour market inequalities, and promoting safe and secure working environments. Access to financial services also needs to be improved to ensure sustained and inclusive economic growth. An integrated approach that addresses the goals of economic growth, for economy, society and the planet, requires resource de-coupling and inclusiveness in order to achieve SDG 8.
    
 The Forum may wish to consider the following recommendations for policy and action. These are based on expert inputs, including the outcomes of the UN Expert Group Meeting on SDG8.
                     Big picture
Sustained economic growth, productivity and jobs creation
Full and productive employment and decent work
Recommendations for policy and action
Leaving no one behind and bold political leadership
Reinvigorate the multilateral system, policy coherence and partnerships
Implement national action plans for achieving SDG 8
Improve education and training systems to align with tomorrow’s needs
Explore new economic growth models for sustainable development and decent work
Recognize the centrality of decent work and SDG 8 as a means and an end for the entire 2030 Agenda and devise integrated policies in that basis
Ethical paradigm needed for further success toward SDG 8.
Develop a new sustainable growth narrative for the 21st century, including new metrics to supplement GDP growth
Expand productive capacities for sustainable development, embrace new business models and new technologies and develop countries’ innovative and learning potential Promote spatially concentrated industrialization efforts
Adopt a human-centred approach to embracing new technologies
Increase productivity in all sectors, with a focus on agriculture and informal sectors Create incentives for entrepreneurship and support MSMEs
Reassert adequate policy space
Develop overall strategic policy frameworks for growth and job creation (including identification of opportunities for labour-intensive manufacturing)
Income redistribution via fair fiscal policy
Pro-employment macroeconomic policies and an enabling environment for sustainable enterprises
Well-functioning labour markets
Governments as significant employer and provider of quality public services
Governments to improve rights and social protection for workers in informal employment
Protect workers’ basic rights, including ILO’s fundamental principles and rights at work, working time, minimum wages, and safety and health
Improve policies for health and safety at work and strengthen workplace cooperation
Enforce labour standards through smart regulations and multi-stakeholder coalitions for a safe and secure workplace for all
Ratify and implement ILO conventions and recommendations
Promote youth employment and participation of young people in decision-making
Integrate persons with disabilities and women into the labour market
Promote life-long learning, skills matching labour market needs, and the transition from school to work and between jobs.
                                                                            
     A just transition, environment, eco- efficiency, sustainable tourism
Decoupling of natural resource use and environmental impacts from economic activity and human well-being
Sustainable consumption and production
Build science-based, international partnerships
Acknowledge the unequal environmental burden on Global South from excess production and consumption in Global North and design partnerships to address problems
Monitor sustainable tourism development
Integrate promotion of SCP and full and productive employment and decent work into sustainable tourism policies
                 Finance, Evaluate international aid and improve access to finance, especially for MSMEs. trade, Strengthen aid for trade and safeguard the multilateral trading system.
     science and technology
Greatly enhance international cooperation on technology.
      Inter- linkages with other SDGs
Share knowledge and good practices to enhance national capacities on integrated SDG8 approaches
Consider SDG linkages and balanced approaches in the global strategy for youth employment (foreseen under SDG target 8.B)
Operationalize SDG8 interlinkages with health, education, inequality, and others
        Data for monitoring, partnerships and capacity building
Promote data accessibility and coherence for SDG 8
Promote national and international, multi-stakeholder partnerships for SDG8. Capacity building for policy coherence
Policy tools needed that measure human-centred development and progress
                 Future challenges and prospects
Shape the impacts of digitalisation with public policies
Greater coherence between macroeconomic, sectoral, structural, educational and social security policies, which needs to be secured in the national action plans (see “big picture”)
Support people through their labour market transitions
Develop actionable visions and strategies for youth-inclusive and decent work-centred development
Embrace artificial intelligence and automation and minimize their adverse consequences
                Guiding questions
The sessions may want to consider addressing the following guiding questions:
1. What progress has been made towards SDG8? What are the most important remaining gaps? What are practical, evidence-based and cost-effective policy recommendations? What are the most important potential future challenges and prospects in the years until 2030?
 
 2. What are the most important interlinkages between SDG8 and the other SDGs that need to be taken into account in devising effective policies in the SDG8 areas? What actions are needed to secure a greater coherence between economic, social, environmental and labour market policies?
3. What do we understand by the terms sustained, inclusive and sustainable economic growth? Can this new way of thinking drive the much needed transformation in the way we approach the economy, society and environment?
4. What are the underlying principles and institutional environment necessary for decent work and SDG 8? How can fundamental principles and rights at work and other labour rights be safeguarded and enhanced towards the achievement of SDG 8?
5. How can we reinvigorate the social contract based on a human-centered approach and ensure that social justice and equality result?
6. How important have finance, trade, science, technology and innovation aspects been for SDG8 progress? How could we more effectively accelerate progress? How will artificial intelligence, automation, bio-tech, nano-tech, digital-tech impact the poorest countries?
7. How can the participation of local authorities, the private sector, civil society and philanthropic organizations, among others, be improved? How can the voices of youth be better reflected in policies and actions? How can the monitoring and data situation be improved? What lessons have we learned from global partnerships related to SDG8?
      
 Background1 Status and trends
Sustained economic growth and productivity
In 2017, real gross domestic product (GDP) per capita grew by 1.9 per cent globally, close to the average growth rate for the years since 2010. Growth projections foresee a continued real growth at about 2 per cent until at least 2020.
For low income countries, the growth rate in 2017 was 1.8 per cent – a notable improvement over the average growth of 0.1 per cent between 2010 and 2016, but well below the average growth rate of 2.6 per cent between 2005 and 2009. The real GDP growth rate for LDCs is expected to increase from 4.5 per cent in 2017 to 5.7 per cent in 2020; which is less than the 7 per cent envisioned by the 2030 Agenda. Only five LDCs reached the SDG 8.1 ambition of sustaining at least 7 per cent GDP growth per year in 2017.
Since the global economic downturn of 2009, labour productivity (measured as GDP per employed person in constant 2005 dollars) has been increasing in the world, recording positive annual growth rates consistently since 2010. In 2017 and 2018, the world’s labour productivity increased by about 2.1 per cent, the highest annual growth since 2010.
Empirical evidence continues to suggest that there is no automatic link between GDP growth and employment or indeed sustained human development. While the global rate of extreme poverty has continued to decline from 16 per cent in 2010 to 8.6 per cent in 2018, the decline has slowed in recent years and is projected to
1 In preparation for the 2019 HLPF, the Division for Sustainable Development Goals of the UN Department of Economic and Social Affairs (DESA/DSDG) in collaboration with the International Labour Organization and UN partners organized an Expert Group Meeting on SDG 8 progress, policies and implementation at ILO Headquarters in Geneva from 3 to 5 April 2019. The outcome of these discussions has informed this background note.
       
 reach 6 per cent in 2030, well above the 3 per cent target. In Sub-Saharan Africa, the share of working poor was still as high as 38 per cent in 2018.2
Full and productive employment and decent work
The global unemployment rate has finally recovered since the global economic crisis. In 2018, the global unemployment rate was 5.0 per cent (which was similar to pre-crisis level), down from 5.6 per cent in 2017, 5.9 per cent in 2009 and 6.4 per cent in 2000.
Informal employment, that impacts adequacy of earnings, occupational safety and health and working conditions, remains pervasive: in three-quarters of countries with data, more than half of all persons employed in non-agriculture are in informal employment. Globally, 61 per cent of all workers were engaged in informal employment in 2016. Excluding the agricultural sector, 51 per cent of all workers fell into this employment category. Working poverty has been falling but remains widespread in some regions.
Workers in the Informal economy suffer from more uncertain, less regular and lower incomes than those in the formal economy, suffer longer working hours and an absence of collective bargaining and representation rights, and often have ambiguous or disguised employment status. Their physical and financial vulnerability is increased by the very fact of working in the informal economy, which is often either excluded from or effectively beyond the reach of social security schemes or safety and health, maternity and other labour rights and protection legislation.
Moreover, half of the world’s population does not yet benefit from freedom of association and collective bargaining. 3 In addition, 152 million children are still in child labour, 40 million persons are in different forms of forced labour and forced
2 see the 2017 Africa regional report on Agenda 2063 and the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) assessment report
3 The Freedom of Association and Protection of the Right to Organise Convention, 1948 (No. 87), and the Right to Organise and Collective Bargaining Convention, 1949 (No. 98), are the least ratified of the ILO’s fundamental Conventions.
       
 marriage and countless persons are excluded from learning opportunities, skills development and decent work because of discrimination by sex, age, disability, political or religious convictions and other factors.
Globally, in 2018, some 64 million young women and men aged 15 to 24 were unemployed, representing a global unemployment rate of 12.6 per cent for this age group – a rate that is more than three times higher than for adults aged 25 and over. Hence. youth are three times more likely to be unemployed than adults. In 2018, one fifth (an estimated 22 per cent) of the world’s youth were not in education, employment or training, meaning that they were neither gaining professional experience nor acquiring or developing skills through educational or vocational programs in their prime years. Globally, young women were over twice as likely as young men to be unemployed or outside the labour force and not in education or training.
The UN Secretary-General’s Sustainable Development Goals Report 2018 – based on 63 countries for which such data was available - estimated the median hourly gender pay gap at 12 per cent. This pay gap exceeds 20 per cent in managerial and professional occupations, among crafts and related trades workers, and among plant machine operators and assemblers.4 Similarly, the ILO Global Wage Report 2018/2019 estimated the global gender pay gap, estimated using average hourly wages, at 19 per cent – an estimate that corrected for the fact that women’s jobs tend to have different characteristics to those of men, especially in countries with low women participation in wage employment.5 The ILO report details gender gaps in education and access to skills, employment and labour force participation, occupational bias and pay, as well as occupational gender segregation, discrimination and stereotyping in the workplace.
Social protection is not a reality for a large majority of the world’s population. In 2016, 55 per cent—as many as 4 billion people—were not covered by any social
4 UN Secretary-General’s Sustainable Development Goals Report 2018
5 ILO: Global Wage Report 2018/19: What lies behind gender pay gaps, 2019.
        
 protection cash benefits, with large variation across regions: from only 13 per cent in sub-Saharan Africa, to 86 per cent in Europe and Northern America. Only 22 per cent of the unemployed receive unemployment cash benefits, 28 per cent of persons with severe disabilities receive disability cash benefits, only 35 per cent of children worldwide enjoy effective access to social protection, and only 41 per cent of women giving birth receive maternity cash benefits.
The ILO estimates that almost 2.8 million workers die every year due to occupational accidents and work-related diseases. Some 2.4 million (86.3 per cent) of these deaths are due to work-related diseases, while over 380,000 (13.7 per cent) result from occupational accidents. Non-fatal injuries are estimated to affect 374 million workers annually, and many of these injuries have serious consequences for workers’ earning capacity in the long term. 6
It is important to note that there are major regional differences. In particular, Africa’s economic growth has not created sufficient jobs to match growing populations and growing demand for jobs. About 60 per cent of jobs in Africa are considered vulnerable. Less than 1 per cent of the unemployed receive unemployment benefits and only 19 per cent of the Sub-Saharan African population is covered by social insurance. The lack of decent jobs, coupled with weak social insurance schemes, have, in turn, contributed to high rates of poverty among the working population. In 2015, 32.1 per cent of working men, compared with 35.1 per cent of working women, were classified as poor.
Financial access and aid for trade
Access to finance is on the rise globally, but the mode of access seems to be changing with growing reliance on technology. From 2010 to 2017, the number of ATMs per 100,000 adults grew by close to 50 per cent from 44 to 66 globally, and from 2.3 to 5.8 in LDCs. Commercial bank branches per 100,000 adults grew
6 P. Hämäläinen, J. Takala and T. B. Kiat: Global estimates of occupational and work-related illnesses 2017 (Workplace Safety and Health Institute, 2017).
       
 by 2 per cent between 2010 and 2017 with more customers using digital banking solutions. In high-income countries, almost every adult has an account at a bank or other financial institution, compared to only 35 per cent of adults in low- income countries. Across all regions, women lag behind men in this regard.
In 2017, aid for trade commitments increased to US$58 billion and more than doubled when compared to the 2002-05 baseline, when they represented US$23.1 billion. In absolute terms, the increase was highest in the agriculture sector (US$1.7 billion), the industry sector (US$1.0 billion) and banking and financial services (US$$1.0 billion).
Challenges and what works
SDG 8 promotes “sustained, inclusive and sustainable economic growth, full and productive employment and decent work for all”. It reaffirms the mutually supportive relationship between economic and social policies, full employment and decent work.
Among others, inclusive and sustainable economic growth, technology, and structural transformation are critical and must be guided by an overall strategic direction. This maybe more crucial than ever, in view of the unprecedented impacts of new technology clusters on all SDG areas and particularly on the future of work and global growth. High levels of inequalities continue as major obstacles to SDG 8 progress.
Achieving many of the other SDGs depends on progress under the SDG 8 targets. Mobilizing the policy priorities, instruments, partnerships and resources that SDG 8- related interventions can bring is therefore crucial for ending all forms of poverty and reducing inequalities, while ensuring that no one is left behind. Furthermore, progress towards SDG 8 alone “means nothing”, if it allows environmental degradation and social exclusion.
There is no substitute for productivity growth or trade-off, heightened productivity growth is needed for job creation. Protection of rights and jobs must happen in tandem with clear creation of employment policies. In many countries, an industry-led economic
      
 transformation still holds the greatest potential for broad-based improvements in labour productivity and, resultingly, decent jobs and affordable products. When framed within supportive legislation and complemented by targeted public policies, it can address the objective of economic growth, resource de-coupling and inclusiveness.
Closing labour-productivity gaps across the national economy and thus avoiding segmented labour markets is probably still an only partially addressed challenge in the majority of low-income countries. It warrants closer cooperation between developing partners and among developing countries to disseminate good practice and facilitate broad-based productivity improvements across countries.
Micro, small and medium enterprises (MSMEs) are crucial for meeting SDG8 and other SDGs. They contribute a major share of total private sector entities in both developed and developing countries, and when the informal sector is included, they account for about 9 out of 10 jobs in developing countries. They are typically the main income source for the poorest population segments, especially in rural areas, and tend to employ a larger share of the workforces in vulnerable sectors. But MSMEs continue to face challenges, including limited access to finance and lack of capacity and knowledge, particularly with regards to business development, marketing and strategic management skills, and, especially in developing countries, also weak political, institutional and regulatory mechanisms.
More exacting and encompassing policy measures are needed to address global and national asymmetries in resource mobilization, technological know-how, market power and political influence caused by hyper-globalization that have generated exclusionary outcomes and will perpetuate them if no action is taken.7
Increased and broad artificial intelligence (AI) deployment will require accelerating the progress being made on the technical challenges, as well making sure that all potential users have access to AI and can benefit from it. Measures that may be needed including further investment in AI research, expanding available data sets, especially where their use would drive wider benefits for society, and encouraging greater AI literacy among
7 UNCTAD (2017)
       
 business leaders and policy makers. A starting point for addressing the potential disruptive impacts of automation will be to ensure robust economic and productivity growth, which is a prerequisite for job growth and increasing prosperity. Governments will also need to foster business dynamism, since entrepreneurship and more rapid new business formation will not only boost productivity, but also drive job creation. AI will not live up to its promise if the public loses confidence in it as a result of privacy violations, bias, or malicious use, or if much of the world comes to blame it for exacerbating inequality.
Full and productive employment and decent work are achievable if the right investments are made, as the recent report of the Global Commission for the Future of Work has emphasized (ILO 2019). To deliver these investments, a set of coordinated policies and institutions based on a strong normative framework is required, along with concrete mechanisms to operationalize, coordinate and govern these policies. Moreover, our perception of what a working life is needs to shift. The familiar three stage life (education, work, retirement) is gone or fading. The new model includes regular periods of training, care responsibilities, career breaks, part- and full-time work. It is imperative that education, employment and social protection systems both reflect and support these new realities. But the world can shape this transformative change – we are not powerless.
The ILO report and the UN's 2030 Agenda set out measures that would increase workers’ rights and prevent exclusions but also envisage a series of investments in material and non-material infrastructure that will help create the best possible environment for companies to thrive and for people to progress toward fairer working and living conditions.
A wealth of data, including from the World Bank and the OECD, shows that not well- regulated overly rigid labour markets, high non-wage labour costs, and excessive bureaucratic burdens hinder companies’ ability to grow and to employ people. What we need are open, dynamic and inclusive labour markets that respect Fundamental Principles and Rights at Work, with simple, transparent, flexible and predictable legal employment frameworks. We also need efficient, speedy and corruption-free processes to register
      
 business and incentives to encourage entrepreneurs to operate in the formal sector are key to encouraging companies to hire, to promoting formalization and to creating chances for underrepresented groups at the labour market.
Big picture
Leaving no one behind and bold political leadership: Bold political leadership is needed to ensure quick and effective implementation of accelerated action to make progress on SDG 8. Progress requires a profound, in-depth appraisal of SDG interlinkages across the dimensions of economy, society and environment. Open policy space is needed, especially for developing countries.
Reinvigorate the multilateral system so that it defends the rights and interests of the poorest and most vulnerable people and creates opportunities for the poorest countries to benefit from globalization. Ensuring policy coherence and strengthening collaboration and partnerships among all stakeholders will be key to facilitate the way forward. More than ever, individuals, social partners, governments, and the civil society, as well as international organisations, need to work together to ensure the achievement of SDG 8.
National action plans for achieving SDG 8. Every government needs to take responsibility for the development and implementation of its national action plan to achieve SDG 8, preferably through a tripartite social dialogue, effective equitable institutions, well-regulated labour markets, and full and equitable access to justice. Member States should consider reviewing their compliance with international norms and standards relevant to the achievement of SDG 8 and develop mechanisms to address potential gaps. Consultations with civil society and the private sector are important, and the strategies need to address the issues of poverty and inequalities, enabling environments for enterprises, new technologies, and a diverse labour force.
Reinvigorated Social Contract: Trade Unions referred to the ILO Global Commission on the Future of Work which called for a reinvigorated Social Contract
      
 for governments, business and workers. The Social Contract should be based on social dialogue to ensure a just transition to a green economy and to deal with displacement effects of new technologies. It might want to aim at a universal labour guarantee, a universal social protection floor for all workers, respect for their rights, including collective bargaining. Jobs need to be decent jobs with minimum living wages, and workers need to have some control over working time. Due diligence and accountability should drive business operations.
Improve education systems to align with tomorrow’s needs. Access to compulsory, high-quality education systems is important to deliver a broad range of essential skills, ranging from core competences, such as literacy and numeracy, to critical thinking, social and behavioural capabilities. Education investment might be focused on early childhood education, especially in low-income countries where preschool attendance is very low.
Explore new economic growth models. Growth models need to look beyond GDP and aim at full employment and structural transformation. Differentiated policy mixes will need to be tailored to specific national circumstance. They should also enable growth from below, in particular in rural economies and informal economies. The trade-offs need to be considered between different SDG aspirations, as well as between long- and short-term policy impacts.
Sustained economic growth, productivity and jobs creation
Develop a new sustainable growth narrative for the 21st century. Such a narrative would focus on economic growth driven by green innovation, investment in sustainable infrastructure, new ‘green’ industries, application of technology to efficient resource management and conservation; on redistribution towards sustainable producers; on new decent jobs for low-carbon sustainable economy transition; on a just transition based on tripartite social dialogue and plans to mitigate negative effects for workers in declining industries and sectors, and to transition them to new skills and jobs. New forms of social protection are needed
      
 for a high-mobility workforce. Ultimately, the new narrative should be based on a reinvigorated social contract.
Expand productive capacities for sustainable development and embrace new technologies and new business models. This is achieved through integrated policies at the domestic and international levels. An industry-led economic transformation still holds the greatest potential for broad-based improvements in labour productivity and, resultingly, increases opportunities for decent jobs and the provision of affordable products. Productivity-enhancing policies need to go hand-in-hand with policies addressing inequalities. Governments, societies and the United Nations should embrace new technologies and direct their development and deployment so that they contribute towards achieving SDG 8 and the overall 2030 Agenda. Externally, this would also allow for measures to promote technology transfer.
Promote spatially concentrated industrialization efforts, especially if designed and managed in close partnership between the public and the private (both domestic and foreign) sector holds unmatched potential to connect developing countries (including least developed ones) into transnational (regional or global) production networks and thus facilitate technology acquisition and modernization of management and marketing functions.
Increase productivity in all sectors, with a focus on agriculture and the informal economy. Governments and the international community need to pay attention to, understand and promote the growth of productivity, and in particular in the small scale agricultural, rural nonfarm, and urban informal sectors, which will determine the economic inclusion of most poor and near-poor people. This should include taking great care when formalising - regulating and taxing the informal economies. Support for countries to have efficient and dynamic labour markets and to better tackle the informal economy.
Create incentives for entrepreneurship and support MSMEs. Coherent efforts are needed to create incentives for entrepreneurship and MSMEs, including
      
 supporting knowledge access and skill building, promoting innovations and access to networks, such as employers and business associations and chambers of commerce. The development community, including the UN system, could support this by providing capacity building, facilitating platforms for exchange of good practices on MSME growth and by supporting cooperation and trade agreements. MSMEs play a vital role in sustainable livelihoods. They need to be integrated into the digital economy and global value chains and should be involved on policy development/strategies. The comprehensive pillars of the ILO Sustainable Enterprises Conclusions deserve consideration.
Reassert adequate policy space. The international community should reassert the need for adequate national policy space in multilateral and other cross-border agreements, including space for industrial policy, public enterprises, regulation and other policies in the public interest. International organizations should provide especially developing countries with sufficient “policy space”.
Overall policy frameworks for growth and job creation (including identification of opportunities for labour-intensive manufacturing). The overarching goal is to promote an enabling environment for sustainable enterprises. Policy frameworks are needed that are based on country specific diagnostics and on effective and responsible social dialogue, with the active engagement of employers' organizations. There is a need to promote productive diversification policies and increase spending on innovation, training, and incorporating new technologies. It is useful to identify and exploit windows of opportunity for labour-intensive manufacturing. In general, a better understanding of how countries can best promote employment-rich industries is needed – for example, to what extent do special economic zones generate sustained escapes from poverty, directly or indirectly and how can their decent work risks be managed?
Pro-employment macroeconomic policies. Countries should boost domestic demand, through fiscal and other policies as a source of employment growth. Full employment should be visibly at the centre of both monetary and fiscal policies,
      
 in the form of demand-stimulating policies, progressive taxation measures and transparent financial systems to fund productive investments and create an enabling environment for enterprises. In addition to strong automatic stabilizers, countries should be capable to promptly put in place and scale up employment guarantees and labour market programmes to sustain income and jobs in the case of downturns and crises. Over the long run, public investments should be used to catalyse productive private investment in technological innovation, productivity enhancements and economic diversification. Public investment can also help realise the potential for jobs and growth in innovative activities in rural areas, in the care sector and in greening the economy (see Future of Work Global Commission report). It will also be important to address the long-term decline in the labour share through collective bargaining and social dialogue. Wages growing in line with productivity do contribute to a stable pattern of consumption and demand. They foster social cohesion and might dampen political instability and its economic downfalls.
Income redistribution. Governments should consider redistributing some income to lower income households with higher propensity to spend and build social protection floors as automatic stabilizers and to lessen the need for precautionary saving by households.
Full and productive employment and decent work
Well-functioning labour markets are key to keeping people in employment and bringing them back into work. These markets need to respect Fundamental Principles and Rights at Work, with simple, transparent, flexible and predictable legal employment frameworks.
Governments as employers of last resort. Governments should also draw lessons from the financial and economic crisis of 2008, when some acted as bankers of last resort but not as employers of last resort. They should now seriously consider the role of the state as the employer of last resort. There should be a deliberate focus to track job creation and Governments should be required to report on
      
 progress being made in ensuring the necessary good conditions are put in place to allow for decent employment opportunities to be created.
Governments to address the challenge of informality. The ILO recommendation R204 provides a detailed road map, including lowering entry barriers due to bureaucratic procedures; simplifying taxation codes; and creating progressive tax structures to encourage small businesses to enter the formal sector.
Need to consider a human-centred approach including fundamental workers’ rights, an “adequate living wage”, limits on hours of work and ensuring safe and healthy workplaces. Such a guarantee could be flanked by a universal social protection from both to old age, based on the principles of solidarity and risk sharing, and underpinned by a protection floor which can be raised through collective agreements and laws/regulations.
Improve health and safety at work. Health and safety at work should be a right of all working people leaving no one behind. A healthy workforce is a prerequisite for sustainable development and economic growth. Therefore, there shall be strong linkages, including co-indicators, between SDG 3 and SDG8 to measure the health benefits of decent work and economic growth. Governments should create measures to stimulate investments in improving working conditions and protecting the health of working people.
Enforce labour standards through improved regulation and multi-stakeholder coalitions for a safe and secure workplace for all, including for women, domestic workers and migrant workers. This relates to more than fair wages. All workers should be adequately protected from the costs of sickness, disability and hazards at work as well as from the risks of informality, abuse and exploitation. It requires multi-stakeholder coalitions for advocacy, awareness and cooperative action, as well as effective enforcement of existing labour market regulations. A critical challenge for many countries is to ensure a minimum of social insurance and social protection afforded to the most vulnerable groups, including those who are engaged in non-traditional forms of employment or in independent employment.
      
 Ratify and implement ILO conventions and recommendations. Member States may want to consider ratifying the ILO conventions which facilitate the attainment of SDG 8, such as conventions 29, 105, 87, 98, 100, 102, 111, 138, 182, 159, 88, and 181. For example, recommendations 87 and 98 deal with freedom of association and collective bargaining, convention 102 and recommendation 202 with universalising social protection systems, recommendation 204 with formalising the informal economy, and recommendation 202 with social protection floors.
Promote youth employment and participation of young people in decision-making.
Promoting youth employment could include regulation to encourage the establishment of apprenticeships systems; and enhancing cooperation between business and VET institutions as well as universities and secondary schools. Young people should be included in the decision-making process in a fair and meaningful way. Trust in institutions is on the decline, and this can only be addressed by working with young people. Policies often still fail to account for the heterogeneity of youth and the contexts they live in. Policies, strategies and interventions towards youth employment need diagnostics, integrated approaches and inter- ministerial coordination while supporting a strong multi-stakeholder inclusion from design stage.
Integrate persons with disabilities and women into the labour market. These should focus on practical measures that contribute to facilitating employment retention and return-to-work opportunities. Support and advice should be provided on how to address the barriers that often prevent persons with disabilities from obtaining jobs in the private sector. In a similar vein, Governments should remove legal and social restrictions that hinder women from participating in the formal labour markets and support formal self-employment opportunities.
Promote life-Long learning and the transition from school to work. Governments need to formalize the role of “learning to learn” in childhood education systems as a fundamental competence and to prioritize lifelong-learning in training and
      
 education systems. Governments should collaborate formally with businesses and business organizations in the design of skill-building and re-skilling initiatives, leveraging new technologies and methods. The link between schools and the world of work need strengthening, addressing skills mismatches and gaps, increasing access to vocational education, while taking into consideration the diverse contexts and needs. Effective education and training institutions need to anticipate labour market needs and adapt to new jobs and rapid technological change.
A just transition, environment, eco-efficiency, sustainable tourism
Decoupling of natural resource use and environmental impacts from economic activity and human well-being is an essential element in the transition to the SDGs. Achieving decoupling is possible and can deliver substantial social and environmental benefits, including repair of past environmental damage, while also supporting economic growth and human well-being. Policymakers and decision makers have tools at their disposal to advance worthwhile change including policies that promote resource efficiency, sustainable consumption and production and circular economy.
Sustainable consumption and production (SCP) provide the approach, tools and solutions for decoupling natural resources use and environmental impacts form economic activity and human well-being. SCP considers the entire life cycle of economic activities, from the extraction of resources, processing these resources into materials and products, the use of these products, and finally their disposal as wastes or emissions. It will require strengthening coordination and policy integration across ministries, engaging those with key economic and financial portfolios, while making SCP part of the institutional culture and body of knowledge of public administrations. SCP is a systems-based approach and in the context of its scope, it may be relevant to use specific sectors as entry points and to support enterprises in this transition, in particular SMEs. Scientific tools and methodologies to identify high impact sectors (“hotspots”), both environmentally
      
 and economically, are available to guide the design of strategic policies with the potential to significantly improve resource efficiency and reduce environmental damages, taking into account socio-economic implications.
Build science-based partnerships. The shift to sustainable economies requires a strong partnership and the contribution of all stakeholders in society for a coordinated action both at global and national level. The broad and systemic transformation will require concerted action from: scientific institutions, businesses, policy makers, civil society, and international organisations. The One Planet network offers such a multi-stakeholder partnership and strengthening existing partnerships is critical to the ambitious timeframe for the implementation of the 2030 Agenda. Further to this, it will be key to ensure partnerships and cooperation with all stakeholders, governmental and non-governmental, at national level to create a sense of national ownership and bring SCP objectives at the heart of the country’s development plan and vision for the future in the context of the SDGs
Monitor sustainable tourism development. Prioritize the development of monitoring mechanisms for the regular and timely measurement of the sustainable development impacts of tourism which make use of new technological solutions in order to overcome the limited availability of data on the social and environmental impacts of the tourism sector both at national and subnational levels and to enhance the accountability for the implementation of policies, maximizing their effective implementation.
Integrate promotion of SCP and full and productive employment and decent work into sustainable tourism policies. Fully integrate in sustainable tourism policies key elements of sustainable consumption and production or “SCP impact areas” (biodiversity conservation and sustainable land-use, energy use efficiency, GHG emissions reduction, waste reduction, and water use efficiency) and policy instruments – as recommended in the UNWTO and UN Environment Baseline Report on the Integration of SCP into tourism policies and to ensure that the
      
 tourism sector can play a key role in the transition to a low-carbon and resource efficient economy. Fully integrate in sustainable tourism policies the promotion of full and productive employment and decent work for all, the promotion of sustainable enterprises, investment in human resource development, the implementation of international labour standards and strengthening labour protection – as recommended in the ILO Guidelines on Decent Work and Socially Responsible Tourism and to take full advantage of the potential of tourism for inclusive economic development and job creation. Encourage development of non-traditional branches of tourism: shift to low-volume, high-value tourism; and shift to pro-poor, eco-friendly tourism.
Ethical paradigm needed for further success toward SDG 8. An ethical paradigm is a precondition for further success towards the SDGs, this also concerns all those involved in the promotion of the SDGs. To this end, we should address the current change in the ethical climate and raise awareness about it on all political and societal levels; install an international body for exchange and monitoring the ethical climate; include religious leaders and other moral authorities in the promotion of the SDGs; encourage religions and secular ethics to make the SDGs part of their agenda; and translate the SDGs into cultural values, so that the SDGs become an integral part of the different cultures’ and peoples’ moral common sense.
Finance, trade, science and technology
Evaluate international aid and improve access to finance, especially for MSMEs.
Most international aid to industry goes to support SME development – financial aid for SMEs and investment climate reforms – which should be subject to multi- stakeholder evaluations. Access to finance remains a serious constraint for MSME growth. This requires the piloting and up-scaling of innovative financing solutions. Targeted capacity building and awareness campaigns should be undertaken to transform the mindsets and attitudes of commercial banks towards MSMEs.
      
 Facilitated access to credit for SMEs can support investments in new equipment and technologies, and in human capital.
Strengthen aid for trade and safeguard the multilateral trading system. Aid for trade should be further strengthened in terms of level and effectiveness, in order to build supply-side capacity and trade-related infrastructure, to diversify exports and to promote the inclusiveness of trade. Retrenching from a rule-based trade system - especially for manufactured products - holds severe risks for SDG8 achievement and many other development goals. Renewed efforts should be made to preserve a multilateral framework for trade negotiations and to align bilateral trade negotiations to maximise the potential for technology diffusion and productive modernization. Understanding the new economic landscape makes us see clearly what should be the trade policy environment in the coming decades. Developing countries could be supported to thrive in the growing “green” and “ethical” trade, i.e., help them add values to their goods and services by incorporating social and environmental considerations in products and promotion. Hence, trade should be a mainstreamed issue in national and sectoral SDG strategies.
Greatly enhance international cooperation on technology. There is much room for much wider and more in-depth technology cooperation world-wide. This will need to comprise many types of cooperation, such as South-South and North-South collaborations, university-Industry collaboration, co-opetition among multinational enterprises, and public private partnerships.
Inter-linkages with other SDGs
Share knowledge and good practices to enhance national capacities on integrated SDG8 approaches. In particular, it would be interesting to provide advisory services, monitor and share good practices on how to enhance policy coherence among interventions targeting poverty (SDG 1), hunger (SDG 2), inequalities (SDG10), and SDG 8. This may include integrated solutions to rural youth
      
 employment promotion through agricultural development, economic diversification, food system transformation, and mobility management.
Consider SDG linkages and balanced approaches in the global strategy for youth employment (foreseen under SDG target 8.B). The global strategy for youth employment (foreseen under Target 8.B) should ensure that adequate linkages are established with key targets under other SDGs that are directly or indirectly conducive to decent work promotion, therefore adopting more integrated multi- dimensional approaches that are guided by the decent work principles. Similarly, the delicate balance need to be explored between work and education; work and inequality and peaceful societies; and work and families.
Operationalize SDG8 inter-linkages with health, education, inequality, and others.
Health and safety at workplaces should be a right of all working people, leaving no one behind. There are obvious interlinkages with SDG8 target issues. Solid and working partnerships are needed, such as the Global Occupational Safety and Health Coalition co-chaired by WHO and ILO, which could be expanded to regional and country levels to systematically work across SDG 3 and SDG 8. Similarly, the universal labour guarantee proposed by the Global Commission on the Future of Work should be linked to the universal health coverage.8 And the SDG8.8 should be linked to the Global Plan of Action on Health and Wellbeing prepared by 10 global health organizations lead by Germany, Norway and Ghana.
Data for monitoring, partnerships and capacity building
Promote data accessibility and data coherence for SDG 8. National partnerships can support data accessibility and data coherence. National statistical producers should be closely linked to policy makers’ needs. They need to allocate sustainable human and financial resources to the production of disaggregated data, using a combination of traditional sources and modern new techniques, such as
8 There will be a High-level Meeting at the UNGA on UHC in September 2019.
       
 geospatial, mobile and administrative “big data”. National strategies are needed for the development of statistics to produce sound, harmonized and timely data.
Promote national and international, multi-stakeholder partnerships for SDG8.
Partnerships across different national government institutions and agencies, at central and local level, private sector organizations, youth organizations and development partners are key for reaching SDG8. Coordination of development partners and international agencies is needed to ensure strong national stakeholder involvement and national capacities, taking into account international standards but allowing for national adaptation. Capacity building programmes are vital in this regard and their efficiency need to be continuously monitored and evaluated. At the national level, governments, parliamentarians, trade unions, the UN, the business sector and civil society should work together, potentially including through multi stakeholder platforms9. In particular they may want to consider ratifying and implementing relevant international legal instruments10; develop national indicators to measure progress towards SDG8 targets; bring domestic legislation in line with the SDG targets (e.g., prohibition of all forms of child labour and modern slavery, forced labour, servitude and debt bondage and access to justice for violations); Increase awareness through public campaigns; and enhance data and monitoring efforts.
Capacity building for policy coherence. Decent work deficits (low income, informality, safety and health hazards, etc.) are still very much present, in particular in rural areas and in the major rural economy sectors like agriculture. Specific attention and strengthening of collaboration between ministries of labour and agriculture should be encouraged. Adequate dissemination of data is a must.
Policy tools needed that measure human-centered development and progress.
Such tools should measure well-being, and take into account environmental, sustainability, and equality issues. Indicators would also include employment-to-
9 e.g., Alliance 8.7
10 such as the 2014 Protocol to ILO Convention 29 on forced labour and the domestic workers convention C189
       
 population ratios; vulnerable employment; the share of working poor in total employment; growth in labour productivity; gender equality for the future of work; inclusive social protection for formal and informal workers; collective worker and employer representation and social dialogue; labour protection on health and safety; and environmental sustainability and equality at work.
Future challenges and prospects
Shape the impacts of digitalization with public policies. Neither positive, nor negative impacts of digitalization on consumption and production are preordained. Public policy is instrumental, particularly in the early formative phase of the development of new technologies and business models, in terms of regulating standards, data access and privacy, monopolies and competition, and above all in infrastructure development and assuring equitable access. The failure of timely regulatory and other policies may render digital revolution to be no longer amiable to ‘social steering’. Most countries, including developing countries, are becoming increasingly aware of the challenges and the potential benefits of the digital revolution. And many are designing strategies to improve the chances of benefiting while mitigating the negative effects while they become ready to tap into these new technologies. But many developing countries need support in order not be left out or marginalized from this great transformation. This would have major impacts on inequality and social stability. With more research and more literature focusing on what developing countries need to do in to face the major challenges to tapping into this new revolution, these dire predictions will hopefully turn more optimistic. The needs for investments in infrastructure that are required are currently beyond the means of many developing countries other than the emerging economies. And the governance that is required to tap into this digital world with appropriate policies and regulations are weak at best.
Greater coherence between macroeconomic, sectoral, structural, educational and social security policies. This requires that attention for work and especially decent work is not only of concern to ministries of labour, but needs to get attention at
      
 the highest political levels. National governments and international financial organizations should target not only growth and stability, but also the creation of decent jobs. An integrated, global vision and goal for labour markets is needed, rather than merely separate national ones. Exact blue prints are not available. However, it might be too late, unless rethinking a renewed social contract does not start now.
Support people through their labour market transitions. Jobs for life are going to be less frequent in the future world of work. It will be a challenge to equip people with the right set of skills at different stages of their work career. Training and work-based learning has become ever more important, leading recently to the call for a universal entitlement to a lifelong learning. In addition, activation strategies and employment services based on modern technologies are important facilitators in the transitions from jobs to jobs.
Develop actionable visions and strategies for youth-inclusive and decent work- centred development. In this regard, national policy development and coordination efforts will be needed and SDG linkages harnessed. The visions and strategies should be informed by evidence and by youth engagement and accompanied by financing plans that include both public and private finance, and by sustained investment in local institutional capacity.
Embrace artificial intelligence and automation and minimize their adverse consequences: Artificial intelligence (AI) needs to be embraced and utilised for good, given its potential contributions to business value, economic growth, and social good. Robust economic, productivity and jobs growth is needed. Addressing the issues related to skills, jobs, and wages will require more focused measures, including rethinking education systems and learning for a changed workplace, stepping up private and public-sector investment in human capital, improving labour market dynamism, and rethinking both incomes and transition support for those left behind by the adoption of new technologies. Confidence into AI needs to be built through strengthening consumer, data, and privacy and security
      
 protections; establishing a generally shared framework and set of principles; sharing best practices; and striking the right balance between the business and national competitive race to lead in AI, to ensure a wide sharing of the benefits of AI. At the same time, many actions may be needed to minimize the adverse consequences of AI and automation. Actions might include installing an international forum for exchange and for monitoring automation, for collecting policies and best practices, and for advising and pressing governments to prepare for automation; strongly supporting developing countries in preparing for and meeting the challenge of automation; developing and implementing policies that foster the ethical, socially and ecologically sustainable use of automation technologies; investing in education (particularly MINT, creativity and social skills); and preparing the workforce for change, and make and keep it agile through adult and lifelong learning.
      
 Annex A: SDG8 goal, targets and indicators11
     Targets under SDG8
 IAEG-SDGs Indicators agreed by Statistical Commission
 Economic growth, technology, and diversification
8.1 Sustain per capita economic growth in accordance with national circumstances and, in particular, at least 7 per cent gross domestic product growth per annum in the least developed countries
 8.1.1 Annual growth rate of real GDP per capita
  8.2 Achieve higher levels of economic productivity through diversification, technological upgrading and innovation, including through a focus on high-value added and labour-intensive sectors
 8.2.1 Annual growth rate of real GDP per employed person
   Global resource efficiency
8.4 Improve progressively, through 2030, global resource efficiency in consumption and production and endeavour to decouple economic growth from environmental degradation, in accordance with the 10-year framework of programmes on sustainable consumption and production, with developed countries taking the lead
 8.4.1 Material footprint, material footprint per capita, and material footprint per GDP. Domestic material consumption, domestic
8.4.2 material consumption per capita, and domestic material consumption per GDP.
     Inclusive Employment
 8.3 Promote development-oriented policies that support productive activities, decent job creation, entrepreneurship, creativity and innovation, and encourage the formalization and growth of micro-, small- and medium- sized enterprises, including through access to financial services.
  8.3.1 Proportion of informal employment in non- agriculture employment, by sex
 8.5 By 2030, achieve full and productive employment and decent work for all women and men, including for young people and persons with disabilities, and equal pay for work of equal value
  8.5.1 Average hourly earnings of female and male employees, by occupation, age and persons with disabilities.
8.5.2 Unemployment rate, by sex, age and persons with disabilities.
8.6
 By 2020, substantially reduce the proportion of youth not in employment, education or training
 8.6.1 Proportion of youth (aged 15-24 years) not in education, employment or training
  8.9 By 2030, devise and implement policies to promote sustainable tourism that creates jobs and promotes local culture and products
   8.9.1 Tourism direct GDP as a proportion of total GDP and in growth rate.
8.9.2 Number of jobs in tourism industries as a proportion of total jobs and growth rate of jobs, by sex
                     11 Source: https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/sdg8
 
    8.B By 2020, develop and operationalize a global strategy for youth employment and implement the Global Jobs Pact of the International Labour Organization
  8.B.1 Existence of a developed and operationalized strategy for youth employment, as a distinct strategy or as part of a national employment strategy.
 Labour rights, health andsafety at work
 8.8 Protect labour rights and promote safe and secure working environments for all workers, including migrant workers, in particular women migrants, and those in precarious employment
  8.8.1 Frequency rates of fatal and non-fatal occupational injuries, by sex and migrant status Increase in national compliance of labour rights
8.8.2 (freedom of association and collective bargaining) based on International Labour Organization (ILO) textual sources and national legislation, by sex and migrant status
 Forced labour, child soldiers, and child labour
 8.7 Take immediate and effective measures to eradicate forced labour, end modern slavery and human trafficking and secure the prohibition and elimination of the worst forms of child labour, including recruitment and use of child soldiers, and by 2025 end child labour in all its forms/
  8.7.1 Proportion and number of children aged 5-17 years engaged in child labour, by sex and age
 Financial access
 8.10 Strengthen the capacity of domestic financial institutions to encourage and expand access to banking, insurance and financial services for all
  8.10. Number of commercial bank branches and
1 automated teller machines (ATMs) per 100,000
adults.
Proportion of adults (15 years and older) with 8.10. an account at a bank or other financial
2 institution or with a mobile-money-service
provider
  Aid for trade
  8.A Increase Aid for Trade support for developing countries, in particular least developed countries, including through the Enhanced Integrated Framework for Trade-Related Technical Assistance to Least Developed Countries
   8.A.1 Aid for Trade commitments and disbursements
              
 Annex B: References and background documents
 Proceedings of the UN Expert Group Meeting on SDG8 – thematic review (Geneva 3-5 April 2019)12 and compilation of policy briefs submitted by experts for the SDG8 review.
 CDP (2018). Expanding Productive Capacity: Lessons Learned From Graduating Least Developed Countries, Policy Note, UN Committee for Development Policy.13
 ILO (2019). Report of the Global Commission for the Future of Work, 21 June 2019.14
 WTO (2018), Mainstreaming trade to attain the Sustainable Development Goals.15
 One Planet Network (2018). Five years in: the One Planet network 2012-2017. Mid-term magazine16. International Resource Panel, 2019. Global Resources Outlook 2019: Natural Resources for the Future We Want.17
      12 https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/index.php?page=view&type=13&nr=3054&menu=1634
13 https://www.un.org/development/desa/dpad/publication/expanding-productive-capacity-lessons-learned-from- graduating-least-developed-countries/
14 http://www.ilo.org
15 https://www.wto.org/english/res_e/booksp_e/sdg_e.pdf
16 http://www.oneplanetnetwork.org/sites/default/files/one_planet_network_mid-term_magazine.pdf
17 http://resourcepanel.org/reports/global-resources-outlook
 